1. Read rt_get_TID() code in rt_Task.c file. Assume that a non-idle task has a task
ID of n, what is the index of this task's TCB in the os_active_TCB array?

n-1

2. Read the rt_TypeDef.h file and answer the following questions.

a) What is the purpose of the p_lnk variable in the struct OS_TCB?

The p_lnk field variable is a pointer to another OS_TCB instance. 
Its purpose is to allow OS_TCB instances to be linked as a linked list.
As we will see, the OS has to manage a priority queue of tasks. 

b) What is the purpose of tsk_stack and stack variables in struct OS_TCB?

The stack field variable points to a block of memory in the stack memory pool. 
Each task has its own stack memory, assigned to it by the OS. 
The stack variable points to the lowest memory address of the corresponding task stack. 

The value of the tsk_stack field variable is the memory address of the top of the task stack.
This is naturally required for stack manipulation, popping and pushing.

c) If you have a variable with type of struct OS_XCB *, will casting this variable
to struct OS_TCB * keep the p_lnk field?

Doing this cast will not preserve the value of the p_lnk field.
Casting a pointer simply reinterprets the bits at the memory address that the pointer is pointing to.
A structure if just a block of memory (bytes) to be interpreted as a collection of different data types. 
The structure OS_XCB has the p_lnk field starting at a one byte offset, because there is a U8 field variables before it.
However the structure OS_TCB has the p_lnk field starting at a five byte offset, because it has four U8 field variables before it.
Therefore accessing p_lnk after the cast is equivalent to accessing a different memory location.

3. Read the rt_Task.c and RTX_lib.c files. What is the purpose of variables mp_tcb and mp_stk?

The global variable mp_tcb is a pointer to a block of memory. This block of memory is used as a memory pool for TCB allocation.

Similarly, the global variable, mp_stk is a pointer to a block of memory which is to be used as task stack memory pool.

Memory pools are used by the OS to "dynamically" allocate memory for new tasks by borrowing memory from the memory pool.
This is to avoid using malloc everytime a new task is created which has expensive runtime overhead.

4. Read Section C.2.3 and study rt_init_stack() and rt_get_PSP() functions source code in HAL_CM3.c file and answer the following questions.

a) Which registers are saved on the task stack?

Registers R1 to R12 , LR and initial PC are pushed onto the task stack.

b) Which bits of which global variable contain the default task stack size in bytes?

The least significant 16 bits of the global variable, os_stackinfo contain the task stack size in bytes (RTX_lib.c line 46).

c) How to determine the memory address of the first item that is pushed onto a task stack?

&(OS_TCB.stk[13]) gives the memory address where the first item pushed onto a task stack resides. 

e init_stack function, the first item pushed onto the task stack may be accessed by stk[13], elsewhere, 
it can be accessed by adding 13*4 (each item is 1 word, 4 bytes, first item pushed is 13 items before the top of stack) to the address stored in tsk_stack field (with OS_TCB).

d) For a task that is not in RUNNING state, how to determine the memory address of the last item that is pushed onto its task stack (i.e. the top of the stack)?

Iterate through os_active_TCB, and check the state for !RUNNING.
The value of the field variable tsk_stack gives the required memory address.

e) For a task that is in RUNNING state, how to determine the memory address of the last item that is pushed onto its task stack (i.e. the top of the stack)?

rt_get_PSP() will return the address corresponding to the top of the task stack, of the one task that is currently running?

5. Read the RTX Library Reference in the Keil IDE Help (see 1.12) and answer the following questions:

a) In an RTX application, how to declare a memory pool named "mympool" that has 20 blocks of memory with block size of 12 bytes?

Use the macro, _declare_box (mympool, 12, 20). See line 20 in RTX_Config.h.

b)  Write one line of code to initialize the "mympool".

_init_box (mympool, 12, 20);


c) What is the corresponding kernel function of _alloc_box()?

void *rt_alloc_box (void *box_mem)  in rt_MemBox.c. 

d) What is the corresponding kernel function of _free_box()?

int rt_free_box (void *box_mem, void *box) in rt_MemBox.c. 

6. Read the rt_TypeDef.h file. What is the purpose of ret_val in the struct OS_TCB?

The field variable, ret_val is set after completion of a wait. 
Its value is an enumeration that describes how the wait has resolved.

7. Read the rt_List.c file and answer the following questions:

a) What does the rt_put_prio() function do?

Inserts a task into a priority queue of tasks. This implies iterating through the list until a suitable spot has been found.
P_XCB p_CB is a pointer to the head of the list. 
P_TCB p_task is a pointer to the OS_TCB structure to be inserted.
  

b) What does the rt_get_first() function do?

Returns the task at the head of the priority queue, that is the one with the highest priority. 
The function returns type P_TCB, given input argument type P_XCB. 

8. Read the rt_Task.c file and answer the following questions:

a) What does the rt_block() function do?

void rt_block(U16 timeout, U8 block_state);
Blocks the task that is currently running and chooses the next task from the priority queue of tasks that are in the READY state (os_rdy). 
The previously running task is timed out and assigned a new state (should not be RUNNING).

b) What does the rt_dispatch() function do?

void rt_dispatch (P_TCB next_TCB);
Takes input type of P_TCB, which is the task that we want to try to dispatch. Three possible outcomes
	1. The pointer is NULL, in which case, switch to the highest priority task that is ready. 
	2. If the specified task, has higher priority than the current running task, then switch tasks.
	3. Otherwise, place the specified task into the priority queue of tasks that are ready.

9. How to set the return value of a function becomes a bit tricky when context switching
is involved. One such example is os_mbx_wait() function. This function will return
OS_R_MBX if the task has waited until a message was put in the mailbox (i.e. the task
was blocked to wait for a message to arrive and then unblocked when the message
arrives). Read the rt_Mailbox.c file and and the lines where the return value
of OS_R_MBX is set. Why the corresponding kernel function rt_mbx_wait() does
not have a line to set the return value to OS_R_MBX? You may skip the code in
functions isr_mbx_receive() and rt_mbx_psh() for the purpose of completing this
assignment.



TODO: Read more about mailboxes, waiting and semaphores before answering this.

10. To block a task, you will need to create a queue that the blocked tasks can stay.
There are two global queues for now in the kernel and they are os_rdy and os_dly.
What data structure do these two queues use?

A priority queue.


